NARRATOR: The spectacular treasures of Tutankhamun,
(music)
Now, for the first time since they were discovered,
The 5,398 objects will be gathered in a new billion-dollar museum.
This will be the first time many of them have been seen in a century.
IKRAM: Look at the horse. Look at the horse, look at the horse.
NARRATOR: Scientists use the latest in scanners and forensic technology
to decipher ancient mysteries, to reveal the man behind the mask.
ECKMANN: Many of the details are visible again.
DR NAUNTON: This wasn't just a huge treasure, it was a real arsenal.
NARRATOR: Not a boy king, but a world-class warrior.
The spectacular Tutankhamun of Egypt.
The Secrets of King Tutankhamun: Rediscovering the Treasure.
The most famous, the most studied pharaoh in history, but even today,
Tutankhamun's treasures still have much to reveal.
Now, the most comprehensive forensic analysis of Tutankhamun's five thousand treasures is underway.
And several key objects have captured the attention of experts.
At the center of the investigation is a mysterious dagger found in the mummified body of Tutankhamun.
Priceless decorations of golden carriages, carefully reconstructed after having been
torn to pieces more than three thousand five hundred years ago.
And the leather remains of a strange armor tunic.
These three treasures will tell us much more about the real Tutankhamun.
Not as a child, but as a warrior.
It is a new chapter in a story that began in the Valley of the Kings,
the afternoon of November 26, 1922.
In the arid desert west of the Nile, British archaeologist Howard Carter
made the greatest archaeological discovery of all time.
The almost intact tomb of an ancient Egyptian pharaoh; Tutankhamun.
Egyptologist Dr. Chris Naunton has been given the unique opportunity
to approach Howard Carter's personal account of the momentous discovery.
DR NAUNTON: This is Howard Carter's diary and it's amazing that I can see it,
because this is the closest you can get to the moment Carter looked at that incredible
set of objects for the first time.
NARRATOR: This meticulously handwritten section records Carter's astonishment.
upon looking into the tomb, becoming the first person to admire
its wonders for more than three thousand five hundred years.
DR NAUNTON: He says, "the interior of the chamber gradually loomed before one with its strange
and wonderful mix of extraordinary and beautiful objects piled up on top of each other.
When Lord Carnarvon said to me, "Can you see anything?"
I replied, "Yes, it's wonderful."
NARRATOR: Tutankhamun's treasures captivated the world.
In the months and years following the discovery, they were carefully excavated
and transferred to the Cairo Museum.
Since then, millions of visitors have marveled at many of the items
found in the tomb of Tutankhamun.
These iconic treasures tell the story of a pampered boy king who died tragically young.
This is the Tutankhamun every student knows; a child too young to rule,
an emotionally manipulated and physically weakened ruler.
But this image is based on a handful of Tutankhamun's treasures displayed at the Museum
from Cairo, which make up only a fraction of the five thousand objects found in his burial chamber.
The rest had been locked away in the museum's basement until now.
The new Grand Egyptian Museum is bringing together all of Tutankhamun's treasures with the aim of
to display the entire collection for the first time since its discovery in 1922.
The treasures in these boxes will reveal new aspects of Tutankhamun's story.
Thousands of objects were packed when they were unearthed and have never been
studied or analyzed, but now in modern laboratories and warehouses
of the Grand Egyptian Museum, all this is about to change.
Behind this simple door lies an Egyptologist's paradise.
RESTORER: This is warehouse 93, welcome, special for Tutankhamun artifacts.
NARRATOR: Filled with priceless treasures and replete with gold, in this room the precious
Tutankhamun's possessions are gathered to be stored and preserved in conditions
climate controlled.
DR NAUNTON: There are some boats, walking sticks. Beds. RESTORATIVE: All of that.
NARRATOR: Chris Naunton is one of a handful of experts who have access.
DR NAUNTON: It's a very exciting time to be here, to see all that material being readied for
the exhibition at the new museum.
It's a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity.
NARRATOR: The last time these treasures were together was inside Tutankhamun's tomb.
Professor Salima Ikram believes that only now, seeing the treasures together,
Egyptologists will be able to begin to tell the full story of the pharaoh's life.
IKRAM: There is too much material in Tutankhamun's tomb.
It's actually like an attic, where people's mothers put their belongings.
to be able to remember them; their entire life is encapsulated from when they were babies onward.
And Tutankhamun's tomb is like opening your attic and being able to look inside into your past life.
NARRATOR: Viewed as a whole, the treasures of Tutankhamun
show a radically new image.
Not a boy king as many believed, this is Tutankhamun the warrior king.
DR NAUNTON: Inside the tomb, Howard Carter found six chariots,
seven throwing sticks, four daggers, dozens of bows, hundreds of arrows,
eight shields and a unique and sophisticated set of armor.
This wasn't just a great treasure, it was a real set of weapons.
NARRATOR: But these were not the toys of a boy-king,
They look like a man's weapons.
IKRAM: People romantically call Tutankhamun the "boy king",
And that's because he came to the throne when he was nine and a half, but died when he was nineteen.
By the age of fourteen in ancient Egypt, one was already a man.
Actually, it is more of a romantic myth to call him a boy-king because he was already an adult king.
truly in that era.
NARRATOR: Nowadays, the history of this king is being rewritten by the artifacts
that was taken to the afterlife.
And there is a treasure that Tutankhamun held in high regard.
Tucked away in a corner of the Cairo Museum lies a small dagger with a big secret.
The most modern technology has revealed new information about this weapon,
which will soon be taken to the Grand Egyptian Museum.
Information that seems to be from another world.
The scale of Tutankhamun's treasure is impressive.
From gilded effigies to elaborate beds and simple items of clothing.
But Tutankhamun was also buried with a large arsenal.
DR NAUNTON: It was drawer, after drawer, after drawer and they all contained arrows.
This entire section is just for this type of object. RESTORER: Yes.
Amazing.
NARRATOR: In this heap from the second millennium BC, there is a weapon that Tutankhamun seemed to treasure.
Since its discovery, this spectacular dagger has been on display in the Cairo Museum.
Tucked away in a corner, on the path of visitors to Tutankhamun's greatest treasures.
DR NAUNTON: It may not be the most famous object discovered in the tomb,
but I think this dagger is one of the most interesting.
NARRATOR: This deadly weapon contains a secret that has been hidden in plain sight.
for almost a century.
Now the dagger has been re-analyzed to present Tutankhamun as a warrior,
hungry for power, in this world and the next.
The dagger was found inside Tutankhamun's sarcophagus.
It rested directly on his body.
DR NAUNTON: This was one of the most important objects for Tutankhamun, apparently.
It was found very close to the mummy, just above its abdomen.
NARRATOR: It is clear that this dagger was special to Tutankhamun, and there is no doubt about its beauty.
DR NAUNTON: The handle is finely decorated with gold, and these bands,
which are inlaid with precious materials, the handle is made of crystal
rock, the case made of beaten gold is decorated with a complex floral pattern.
NARRATOR: Tutankhamun's tomb was filled with gold and gems.
Why was this dagger buried inside his sarcophagus, with his body?
What made her so precious?
The answer lies in the blade of the dagger.
DR NAUNTON: Perhaps the most interesting aspect in fact is the blade,
which is composed of iron.
NARRATOR: Iron is one of the most common elements on Earth,
But in Tutankhamun's Egypt, iron was rarer than gold.
DR NAUNTON: Three thousand five hundred years ago, iron was almost non-existent in Egypt.
We have no archaeological evidence of iron smelting in this part of the world.
until the 6th century BC.
NARRATOR: It is 800 years after Tutankhamun died.
The iron in the dagger blade was not mined or smelted in Egypt.
So where did it come from?
The mystery has baffled experts since the dagger's discovery nearly a century ago.
But until recently, there was no way to know where the iron came from.
of the blade without destroying it.
Now, thanks to the use of advanced non-destructive X-ray analysis,
Restorers may discover new aspects of this ancient mystery.
Because there's more than iron in this blade.
DR NAUNTON: This technique allows us to see the unique chemical fingerprint of the blade of this dagger.
And the crucial thing is that it tells us the percentage of the various different elements.
ELNAGGAR: He is ready for the test.
NARRATOR: Iron exists in nature mixed with other elements,
and this mixture is unique to each source of the metal.
By identifying the blade's unique chemical fingerprint, restorers were able to
to determine its origin.
ELNAGGAR: I need everyone to step back three meters please.
for health and safety because we are now going to perform the X-rays.
NARRATOR: The machine fires high-energy X-rays at the dagger's blade,
and it is the energy that is reflected back that reveals the elements contained within.
ELNAGGAR: Okay, done.
What we have now is the result of the X-ray test,
and we can see here the elements of the chemical composition and you can see three peaks,
which are made of iron, nickel and cobalt.
DR NAUNTON: Okay.
NARRATOR: What the restorers discovered was that the proportion of nickel
was unusually tall.
DR NAUNTON: What does that tell us about the type of iron that was used to make the dagger?
ELNAGGAR: This type of chemical composition is not found in cast iron
from Egypt, or even on the planet.
NARRATOR: There is no match on Earth for the iron in this dagger.
DR NAUNTON: If this iron doesn't come from this planet, where does it come from?
ELNAGGAR: It can only come from meteorites.
DR NAUNTON: From a meteorite? ELNAGGAR: Yes, that's how it is.
NARRATOR: The iron in Tutankhamun's dagger is extraterrestrial.
Their journey began thousands, perhaps millions of years ago.
From the asteroid belt between Mars and Jupiter at more than 400 million kilometers
A chunk of rock and metal descended faster than a bullet, towards Earth.
It crashed into the planet's surface, breaking into fragments of molten iron.
Somewhere in the dunes of Africa, these fragments lay for thousands,
even millions of years, until they were discovered and collected to be melted down,
forged and transformed into an object of singular beauty and power.
The iron in this dagger has had an extraordinary journey.
Egyptologist Aidan Dodson believes that Tutankhamun knew that this iron fell from the heavens.
DODSON: Fifteen or two thousand years before Tutankhamun, there was talk of iron from the sky.
like some kind of miracle material.
Iron has power. It comes from the gods.
NARRATOR: To Tutankhamun, the dagger must have seemed like a gift from the gods.
Now, another set of hidden artifacts, not seen in their original glory for three thousand years.
Five hundred years ago, new information about Tutankhamun's ambitions is revealed.
A unique combination of images showing him as a powerful ruler
not only of Egypt, but of the world.
Tutankhamun took six chariots to the next life, carefully dismantled
and piled up in the antechamber of his tomb.
When Howard Carter discovered the tomb, he found at least fifteen hundred tiny pieces
of gold under the carriage.
I didn't have the technology to deal with these bewildering metal fragments,
So he put them in a box in the hope that someone in the future would do the same.
Now, decades later, those golden fragments have finally been reassembled.
World-renowned gold restorer Dr. Christian Eckmann,
has been putting the pieces together.
His work reveals a series of striking images that show Tutankhamun at the center of the world.
ECKMANN: Many tiny details are visible again,
that were not visible when they were excavated.
NARRATOR: Eckmann discovered that these fragments are parts of gold panels used
once used as decorations on the harnesses and ornaments of Tutankhamun's chariots.
These amazing and fragile puzzle pieces have taken three years
to be armed.
ECKMANN: Each of the pieces, which we could reposition on the gold leaf,
is another part of a big puzzle.
But there are still missing pieces and of course we try to put those little pieces together.
in its original position.
NARRATOR: Eckmann has pieced together at least 70 intricate gold panels.
in relief, made to decorate six leather harnesses for carriages.
And that would have made a powerful impression on anyone who saw them.
These images had not been seen since the doors were sealed in the tomb
of Tutankhamun three thousand five hundred years ago.
For Egyptologist Professor Salima Ikram, interpreting them is an incredible privilege.
IKRAM: This material is fabulous, because it has never been exhibited before despite
come from the tomb of the famous king, Tutankhamun.
NARRATOR: Salima has been decoding these images, designs that reveal that the
Tutankhamun's ambitions extended beyond the borders of Egypt.
IKRAM: The leather of Tutankhamun's chariots is unusual and this is because it has no images
propaganda normals.
At first glance, you think they are some kind of animals fighting each other,
but then you realize there's a griffin involved, which is an animal from the Near East,
There are plants belonging to the Syrian tradition, and then there is this spiral current,
which is Aegean. There is a cocktail
of great empires and great artistic traditions in conjunction.
NARRATOR: These foreign designs were deliberately chosen
to present Tutankhamun as a player on an international stage
and as the most powerful ruler of the ancient world.
IKRAM: This combination of styles seems to emphasize the fact that I wanted to show
that his power covered a lot of territory so to speak and he could control
all kinds of places and people.
NARRATOR: The gold decorations on the harnesses suggest that Tutankhamun wanted to be seen as
an international politician, and a chariot that is about to be moved to the Grand Egyptian Museum
shows how prepared he was to go in search of that power.
DR NAUNTON: This carriage will be 3D scanned today.
The first thing that has to happen, of course, is that this box, which has protected it for decades,
will be dismantled right in front of us.
NARRATOR: For Egyptologist Chris Naunton, it's a surprising opportunity
to examine the luxuriously decorated surfaces of the carriage.
Before it is moved, the current condition of the carriage must be rigorously checked.
analyzed.
DR NAUNTON: What's happening is this handheld device is being used to take
a quick succession, a sequence of images that create a digital model of the float
and this is very important because we need to understand the condition,
the shape of the float in its current condition so that it can then be re-evaluated
when it is taken to the new Grand Egyptian Museum.
NARRATOR: The detailed digital model will ensure the remains of the hearse are in the same condition.
after she is transferred.
DR NAUNTON: One of the things that is amazing about being so close to these objects,
is that you can appreciate the incredible and fine details.
NARRATOR: Few people can get past the protective glass to study this hearse.
It's a rare opportunity to see how the young pharaoh wanted the world to see him.
DR NAUNTON: What we can see here is that some of the exquisite decoration
The interior of the carriage is covered in beaten gold and displays a frieze of foreign prisoners,
enemies of Tutankhamun.
NARRATOR: But these beautiful decorations portray graphic brutality that indicates that
Tutankhamun would stop at nothing in his pursuit of power.
DR NAUNTON: There's a rope, which runs all the way around the scene, and which ties them all together.
Some have it tied around their neck, some have their hands behind their back,
Some have their hands tied at the wrists and above their heads.
NARRATOR: The intricate details and distinctive outfits identify the prisoners.
like Egypt's traditional enemies, from the south and the north.
DR NAUNTON: I was trying to convey the idea of being ruler of all foreign people.
that surrounded their country.
NARRATOR: Armed with an iron dagger of the gods, and proclaiming his power from
a carriage decorated with golden images of its international supremacy,
Tutankhamun set out to dominate the ancient world.
But these treasures seem to be too beautiful for the battlefield.
Was all this just to impress?
A king playing soldier?
Or was it a real warning that Tutankhamun was a serious warrior king?
Now, groundbreaking research into the mysterious armored tunic found
inside Tutankhamun's tomb, could provide an answer.
SKINNER: It was actually a piece of modern military equipment.
NARRATOR: This is the critical piece of the puzzle that could prove how prepared
that Tutankhamun was going in search of power.
And that creates the possibility that Tutankhamun was willing to go to war.
(music)
In the modern laboratories of the Grand Egyptian Museum, the ancient leather specialist,
Lucy Skinner has come to see one of Tutankhamun's most intriguing treasures.
This unique armor vest could help prove something extraordinary; that Tutankhamun,
dismissed for nearly a century as a powerless boy-king,
was willing to go to war.
SKINNER: Vaya.
NARRATOR: These are the remains of Tutankhamun's personal armor tunic.
It would have been an impressive and intimidating sight.
Now, three thousand five hundred years after she was buried with Tutankhamun,
and after almost a century in storage, it was moved to the Grand Egyptian Museum.
For Lucy, it's her first chance to examine the armor up close.
SKINNER: It's great to see her like this.
I've been working with ancient Egyptian leather for a decade, and I can finally look at this object. In fact, that piece...
NARRATOR: Nothing like it has been found from ancient Egypt.
Lucy thinks that understanding how the armor was created will provide more insight into its purpose.
And show whether it was created to intimidate or for battle.
At least two thousand leather scales were sewn together and overlapped.
The edges prevented the flakes from separating.
The result was a strong and flexible armor.
SKINNER: You can clearly see how the edges on each scale are
are superimposed on each other.
If an arrow were to hit the armor, these edges would somehow prevent it from falling apart.
This gives you additional protection.
NARRATOR: Lucy believes that the sophisticated manufacturing technique made the armor
was strong and flexible.
A practical piece of equipment rather than a ceremonial item.
And to confirm her theory, Lucy wants to examine two similarly sized scales in detail.
SKINNER: This technique is called light reflection transformation scanning.
It is a scanning process in which a series of photographs are taken with different
lighting angles and then the shadows and highlights of each image are amalgamated
in one, and that brings out the details, and makes the details really clear
on the surface of the object.
This is great because we can see the true texture of the surface.
NARRATOR: This is the first time these scales have been examined using forensic techniques.
And Lucy immediately notices an uncanny similarity between the two scales.
SKINNER: Zoom in a little closer. ANALYST: The right one?
SKINNER: These scales are almost the same, right?
Same size, same width, the edges are in the same position.
They are extremely consistent.
That suggests that they actually found an optimal method for doing these things.
and then they played it over and over and over again.
NARRATOR: For Lucy, the best explanation for the similarity between the scales is that they were
made using a mold.
SKINNER: The center edge can be seen to be very defined.
It is clearly seen that it was made with some pressure in a mold.
NARRATOR: Molding the leather would make the scales consistent, thick, and strong.
Lucy believes one reason for doing this would be to make Tutankhamun's armor ready for battle.
SKINNER: The way the surface looks so compact, it's definitely,
would deflect a big impact, I think.
NARRATOR: Ingeniously designed and meticulously manufactured,
This armor was created to resist arrows.
Lucy believes it wasn't to impress, it was for war.
And Tutankhamun may have used it on the battlefield.
SKINNER: It was actually a very modern piece of military equipment.
It was almost like the Kevlar vest of the ancient Egyptian world.
NARRATOR: A true warrior facing a real threat would want armor like this,
But who was Tutankhamun planning to fight?
Who did he feel threatened by? And why?
In the storerooms of the new Grand Egyptian Museum, Egyptologist and professor Salima Ikram found
an arch belonging to Tutankhamun that displays his worst enemies.
IKRAM: Heavens.
We've never seen anything like this before.
EXAMINER: It's the first time. RESTORER: that it's been seen.
NARRATOR: Since its discovery almost a century ago,
This arch had been kept in the basement of the old Cairo Museum.
IKRAM: This is the tip of the bow, because it has the enemies from the north
and below are the enemies from the south.
The Nubians are to the south and several Asians to the north, and in fact sometimes the Libyans too.
NARRATOR: Salima believes this bow was never shot in anger,
It's too beautiful for the battlefield.
But it is a critical clue in the story of Tutankhamun, because it reveals a country, and a pharaoh, under threat.
To the south, insurgencies in the colony of Nubia threatened Egypt's gold supply.
and precious goods from Africa.
To the northwest, Libyan tribes made violent incursions into Egyptian territory.
And to the east, the aggressive Hittite Empire was advancing through Syria, getting ever closer.
to the borders of Egypt.
DR NAUNTON: Egypt was in turmoil.
His allies had become enemies and expansionists.
The aggressive Hittites were very close to Egypt.
NARRATOR: That's why Tutankhamun was buried with a whole arsenal.
In addition to the celestial dagger and the modern armor, the restorers of the Grand Museum
Egyptian unpack dozens of functional bows, hundreds of arrows,
shields and throwing sticks.
Together, they tell the story of Tutankhamun as a warrior-king, with the equipment and motivation
to go to war.
This is forcing Egyptologists to take a new look at all of Tutankhamun's treasures.
Even those that have been on display in the old Cairo Museum for decades.
Could Tutankhamun's true identity have been hidden in plain sight?
Was the warrior king in front of us the whole time?
IKRAM: This is a box from Tutankhamun's tomb and is decorated on all sides.
with scenes of the king in his chariot chasing enemies.
NARRATOR: And he wages battle using the same weapons as the Egyptologists and scientists
are being analyzed at the Grand Egyptian Museum.
The great bow, arrows, and the armor tunic.
The decorated harnesses and the carriage.
IKRAM: Here the king is shown riding his chariot, and then he takes out this huge bow and attacks,
and all the enemies of the south are struck by his arrows and fall at his feet.
(shouting)
What's great is that, on the other side, something very similar is happening,
but with the enemies of northern Egypt.
These are people with big beards from the Syrian area, and they are being trampled
by the king's horses, they push them under the wheels of the chariots.
And again, Tutankhamun attacks with his bow as he advances.
NARRATOR: This is Tutankhamun, the warrior-king at the center of the battle, leading from the front.
IKRAM: You get a sense of the landscape, and the chaos and the situation.
It's fantastic.
NARRATOR: Since its discovery almost a century ago,
The images on this box have been considered fantasy, but the weapons presented
In the box are the same weapons found in Tutankhamun's tomb.
So if the weapons shown here were real,
Were these events real too?
Are these violent battle scenes closer to reality than some people think?
had you thought about it before?
Did Tutankhamun lead Egypt's armies into battle?
The answer lies outside the Grand Egyptian Museum, on the banks of the Nile in Thebes,
in the spectacular ruins of the Luxor temple.
This was the religious capital of ancient Egypt, and all the pharaohs wanted to leave their mark.
Here, recycling and recarving the rocks of previous buildings.
DR NAUNTON: We don't have much evidence of Tutankhamun's buildings,
but we do have fragments here and there that suggest that perhaps he erected temples, and if he did,
would have included battle scenes like this one.
NARRATOR: Today, Tutankhamun's battle sculptures are scattered throughout the site.
They are pieces of a colossal and seemingly impossible three-dimensional puzzle.
Archaeologist Ray Johnson has spent 20 years painstakingly recording and reassembling
digitally recreates Tutankhamun's battle scenes with fascinating results.
Exciting vivid details include severed hands threaded onto rods
and a caged prisoner hanging from the mast of a ship.
Egyptologist Aidan Dodson believes these engravings are more than just propaganda as many had believed.
DODSON: The nature of these reliefs is such that they do not appear to be stereotypes,
appear to be specific, and therefore I think it might be a reasonable case that these blocks
from Luxor report a particular campaign.
NARRATOR: And in this campaign, Tutankhamun is the main character.
DODSON: It seems likely that the king was physically involved in these campaigns,
and there is no reason to assume that the king, if shown there, was not in fact there.
NARRATOR: Some Egyptologists now believe that these shattered stone fragments
record real historical events, and that the image of Tutankhamun as a fragile
boy-king must be re-evaluated. DR NAUNTON: He would not be,
In that case, a kind of weak subject unable to walk,
could not have participated in any kind of athletic event.
Instead we would be seeing a young, strong and vigorous warrior.
NARRATOR: The celestial dagger and the decorated chariot reveal a power-hungry man.
The large arsenal and modern armor suggest that he was ready to fight.
And the painted box and carved battle scenes are powerful evidence
that Tutankhamun led his armies into battle.
Together, these treasures suggest a different image of the world's most famous pharaoh;
that of a warrior king who may have gone to war and possibly never returned.
In the laboratories of the new Grand Egyptian Museum, history is being reexamined
and the image of Tutankhamun as a warrior king has emerged.
A power-hungry man, protected by modern armor,
and a magic iron dagger of the gods.
Leading the front in the heat of battle.
A man who died at the age of 19.
Did the young pharaoh die in battle?
Did Tutankhamun make the ultimate sacrifice?
In the Valley of the Kings, inside the tomb where he was laid to rest
Three thousand five hundred years ago, lies the mummified body of Tutankhamun.
For thirty-three centuries, oils and resins have preserved its body and its secrets.
During the last century, since the discovery of his tomb,
A debate has erupted over the cause of his death.
IKRAM: There has been endless speculation about whether he had malaria.
and if he had sepsis and that killed him.
Or if he had been hit on the head.
Actually, a lot has been written about this.
NARRATOR: Instead, Salima believes the key to discovering what killed Tutankhamun
It is not about investigating how he died, but where.
And she believes this X-ray of Tutankhamun's skull holds a clue.
IKRAM: Here is your skull, this is one layer of resin and this is a second layer of resin.
The fact that there are two distinct layers of resin suggests that Tutankhamun was mummified in
a kind of two-part process, which is very unusual.
NARRATOR: Mummification needed to begin within a few days of death.
IKRAM: What should be done immediately is to empty the body of internal organs and sometimes
even the brain, because otherwise bacteria get in it and it swells up and could explode.
NARRATOR: The two-part process could be a sign that Tutankhamun was mummified.
temporarily to prevent decomposition before complete mummification could be performed.
IKRAM: It is possible that he died far from the Nile Valley and a kind of
of initial mummification.
It could be that he was on an expedition of some sort, or it could be because he was
fighting in some sort of campaign in the not-so-nearby Nile Desert.
NARRATOR: A chest X-ray reveals something even stranger.
IKRAM: There is something very obvious missing, because there is no heart, and the Egyptians always left
the heart in the body because you must have it to be able to make the transition between this world
and the next one.
The absence of the heart could suggest that whoever carried out the mummification was not so
as right-handed as he should have been, or that Tutankhamun needed immediate attention far from where
the best embalmers were there.
NARRATOR: Evidence suggests that Tutankhamun may have died far from home.
By the end of 1323 BC, Egypt's armies were twelve hundred strong.
kilometers away from home, in northern Syria, fighting against their arch-enemies, the Hittites.
If Tutankhamun was the warrior-king that the evidence suggests,
odds are he could have been there too.
DODSON: We know that Egypt was involved in military activities
northern Syria.
Whether or not Tutankhamun was leading the army deep into Syria,
It can be argued that he was indeed in Syria with the Egyptian army,
seems somewhat persuasive.
NARRATOR: Tutankhamun may have fought and died in this campaign in a distant corner of the Egyptian empire.
Stopped in the prime of his life as a warrior king.
DR NAUNTON: Perhaps Tutankhamun died just as he was leaving his mark,
had begun to recover foreign territory that had been lost in order to reestablish
to Egypt as the great power of the region.
And who knows, if he had lived perhaps he would have had a great and glorious reign.
and his dynasty would have lasted a long time, and history would have been very different.
NARRATOR: As the thousands of Tutankhamun's treasures are gathered in the new Grand Museum
Egyptian, many present the image of a young pharaoh determined to leave his mark
from Egypt to the world.
A heavenly knife, one of his most personal and prized possessions.
Gold decorations on newly restored chariots depicting an international ruler.
And a novel armor that suggests he was ready to fight for his country.
Together they tell the story of Tutankhamun as a warrior, not a boy, but a man,
who perhaps made the ultimate sacrifice.